A Finding Aid to the Hermann Dudley Murphy Papers, circa 1878-1982, in the Archives of American Art aaa.murpherm
Archives of American Art
Hermann Dudley Murphy papers
circa 1878-1982
aaa.murpherm
Archives of American Art
2.8 Linear feet
The papers of painter and frame maker Hermann Dudley Murphy measure 2.8 linear feet and date from circa 1878-1982. Found are biographical materials, correspondence, writings, personal business records, printed materials, a scrapbook, photographs, and original artworks, including sketchbooks.
Murphy, Hermann Dudley, 1867-1945
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated in 1985 by Alexander B. and Dudley D. B. Samoiloff, grandsons of Hermann Dudley Murphy.
Existence and Location of Originals note
Several letters from Caroline Bowles Murphy to Hermann Dudley Murphy are photocopies. The original materials stayed with the donor, Alexander Samoiloff.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter and frame maker Hermann Dudley Murphy measure 2.8 linear feet and date from circa 1878-1982. Found are biographical materials, correspondence, writings, personal business records, printed materials, a scrapbook, photographs, and original artworks, including sketchbooks.
The bulk of the papers focus on the later part of Herman Dudley Murphy's career. Specifically, correspondence focuses on the sale of still-life paintings and sketches and sketchbooks are mostly from Murphy's travels through Europe and Mexico from the 1920s to the 1930s. Correspondents include: Mary Ogden Abbott, Edwin S. Barrie, Maurice Prendergast, Chauncey Ryder, Theodore Sizer, Edmund Tarbell, Alexander Trowbridge, and Vose Gallery among others. Personal business records comment on the sale of works of art from 1897 until 1944. Printed materials include clippings and exhibition catalogs spanning Murphy's career. One scrapbook contains photos and printed materials. Photographs and snapshots are of Hermann Dudley Murphey and family, family travels, and works of art and frames. Artwork consists of loose sketches, prints, and sketchbooks.
Biographical/Historical note
Hermann Dudley Murphy (1867-1945) was a painter and frame maker active in Boston, Massachusetts.
Hermann Dudley Murphy was born in Massachusetts in 1867. He studied art under Edmund Tarbell at the Boston Museum School and later in Paris at the Académie Julian. His early career focused on portraiture and landscape painting. While in Paris, Murphy learned to make frames for artworks. After exhibiting at the 1913 Armory Show, Murphy rejected Modernism and painted still-life. He was known for his Tonalist style and his floral still-life paintings which included objects d'art such as Chinese ceramics, bronze statues, and textiles. Additionally, Murphy taught art classes at the Harvard School of Architecture and the Worcester Art Museum School.
Murphy married Caroline Bowles Murphy with whom he had two children, Carlene and Dudley Murphy. After Caroline died, he married artist Nellie Littlehale. With Nellie, he shared an interest in deck-seat canoeing. Murphy died in 1945.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 8 series.
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1887-circa 1940 (Box 1; 7 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1890-1962 (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, circa 1900-1942 (Box 1; 7 folders)
Series 4: Personal Business and Financial Records, 1897-1944 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1889-1982 (Box 1-2; 0.9 linear feet)
Series 6: Scrapbook, circa 1910 (Box 2; 1 folder)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1878-circa 1950 (Box 2; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 8: Artwork, 1892-circa 1940 (Box 2-4; 0.8 linear feet)
Abbott, Mary Ogden, 1894-1981; Barrie, Erwin S., 1886-1983; Prendergast, Maurice Brazil, 1858-1924; Ryder, Chauncey F., 1868-1949; Sizer, Theodore, 1892-1967; Tarbell, Edmund Charles, 1862-1938; Trowbridge, Alexander Buell, 1868-1950; Vose Galleries of Boston; Mexico--Description and travel; Painters; Photographs; Picture frames and framing--Massachusetts; Prints; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Sketches
- Biographical Materials, 1887-circa 1940; Series 1; 7 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Found are scattered biographical materials including an address book; appointment and discharge letters for the building of a canal in Nicaragua; meeting minutes for the art commission of Massachusetts; and a Who's Who questionaire. Also found are materials relating to others including funeral memorial designs by Hermann Dudley Murphy for family; Nellie Murhpy's passport application; and certificates and a medal for Ettore Caser.
  - Address Book, circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Nicaragua Canal Construction Material, 1887-1888 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Commonwealth of Massachusetts, Art Commission Material, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Who's Who Questionaire, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Funeral and Memorial Material for Others, circa 1923-1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Nellie Murphy Material, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ettore Caser Material, 1916-1918 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, circa 1890-1962; Series 2; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  Found is personal and professional correspondence. Early correspondence is scattered and includes letters to and from Hermann Dudley Murphy's family. Mostly, correspondence from the 1930s and 1940s is professional in nature and discusses Murphy's consignments and sales. Correspondents include: Mary Ogden Abbott, Art Institute of Chicago, Edwin S. Barrie, Ettore Caser, Cleveland Museum of Art, Gennaro Favai, Findlay Galleries, Richmond Fletcher, Grand Central Galleries, James Newman, Maurice Prendergast, Chauncey Ryder,Theodore Sizer, Edmund Tarbell, Alexander Trowbridge, and Vose Gallery.
  - Hermann Dudley Murphy to His Children, circa 1920 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Caroline Murphy to Hermann Dudley Murphy (photocopies), circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1890s, 1892-1899 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1900s, 1904-1909 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1910s, 1912-1919 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1920s, 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - 1930s, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 15-19)
  - 1940s, 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder 20-24)
  - circa 1890-circa 1945, 1890s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Carlene Samoiloff, 1945-1962 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1900-1942; Series 3; 7 Folders Box 1
  Found are writings by Hermann Dudley Murphy including a poem and lists, and writings by others.
  - Poem for Caroline Bowles Murphy, by Herman Dudley Murphy, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Lists of Works of Art, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Lists, 1930-circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "The Rabit [sic]," by Carlene Bowles Murphy Samoiloff, circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - "The Loss of Style," by Ettore Caser, circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Unknown Writings, by Others, circa 1900-circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 32-33)
- Personal Business and Financial Records, 1897-1944; Series 4; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Found are consignment, loan, and sales records from Grand Central Galleries; acknowledgements of gifts from Museum of Fine Arts, Boston and Harvard University; three sales ledgers, one of which includes annotated exhibtion catalogs; and a file entitled "Bat File" which includes correspondence, and unsigned sketches of plans, possibly for an unidentified commission.
  - Consignment, Loan, and Sales Receipts, 1939-1944 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Gift Acknowledgements, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Sales Ledgers, 1897-1943 (Box 1, Folder 36-38)
  - "Bat File", 1906 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Includes unsigned plans, sketches, and correspondence.
- Printed Material, 1889-1982; Series 5; 0.9 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Found are clippings relating to Hermann Dudley Murphy's career as a frame maker and painter; exhibition catalogs for solo and group shows featuring Hermann Dudley Murphy; published works by Mrs. Schuyler van Rennselaer, Denman W. Ross, and Otto H. Kahn; various art publications; and exhibition catalogs, announcements, and reproductions of works of art for Gennaro Favai.
  - Clippings, 1898-1982 (Box 1, Folder 40-48)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1906-1913 (Box 1, Folder 49-53)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1914-1982 (Box 2, Folder 1-9)
  - Published Books by Others, 1893-1916 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - Various Art Publications, 1889-1936 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Gennaro Favai Material, circa 1920 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Scrapbook, circa 1910; Series 6; 1 Folders Box 2
  Found is one scrapbook consisting of: photographs of Hermann Dudley Murphy and household pets; clippings; sketches; and reproductions of works of art.
  - Scrapbook, circa 1910 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Photographs, circa 1878-circa 1950; Series 7; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  Found are portraits and snapshots of Hermann Dudley Murphy, Caroline Bowles Murphy, Nellie Littlehale Murphy, Carlene and Dudley Murphy, friends, and colleagues; and snapshots from canoeing trips taken by the Murphy family. Also found are photos of works of art and frames by Hermann Dudley Murphy.
  - Portraits of Hermann Dudley Murphy and Family, circa 1878-circa 1940 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Includes photos of Caroline Bowles Murphy, Carlene Murphy, and Dudley Murphy.
  - Portraits of Friends and Colleagues, 1895-circa 1920 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Includes photos of Ettore Caser, Robert Coit, Fred Holland Day, John Enister, and Charles Hopkins.
  - Canoe Trip Snapshots, circa 1891-1927 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Works of Art, circa 1890-circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 18-25)
  - Frames, circa 1915 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Negatives, circa 1940 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Artwork, 1892-circa 1940; Series 8; 0.8 Linear feet Box 2-4
  Found are loose pen and ink, pencil, and watercolor sketches; and sixteen sketchbooks including those from Murphy's travels through Europe and Mexico. One of the sketchbooks is annotated and describes steps to making frames.
  - Loose Sketches and Prints, circa 1900-circa 1940 (Box 2, Folder 28-30)
  - Sketchbooks, 1892-circa 1940 (Box 3, Folder 1-9)
  - Sketchbooks, 1892-circa 1940 (Box 4, Folder 1-5)